I was overwhelmed with
grief, fear and anxiety;
Ashley Dalton MP
Labour · West Lancashire
I was scared of
what was to come,
and fearful of how
it would impact
my family and my loved ones.
I was scared that
I was going to
get really poorly and
thinking, "How will I cope?
How will my family cope?
How will I be cared for?
How will I afford it?
How badly will it hurt?
How long will it last?"
When you hear those words,
depression, anxiety,
grief, fear,
shame and guilt
come in bounds.
Suicide risk is highest
immediately after diagnosis,
and it usually falls quickly,
within three to six months.
I would be lying
if I said that when
thinking about all
that was to come,
I did not consider
that it might be fairer
and easier on everyone
if I just got the
dying over with as
soon as possible.
The soft language of "assisted
Carla Lockhart MP
DUP · Upper Bann
dying" is misleading
the public,
because it obscures
the stark and very dark
reality of what is
actually being proposed.
We should always
have the courage
to call things what they are.
Of course, we all want
assistance when we are dying,
but that is not what
this Bill provides.
It is not about
an extra shot of
morphine to ease
someone on their way;
it is a Bill that allows
doctors to provide
lethal drugs for a
patient to end their life.
Let the reality of that
sink in: our great NHS,
the principles of which are
to protect and to save lives,
would be responsible for
state-sponsored suicide.
That is what it is.
I previously voted
for assisted dying.
Janet Daby MP
Labour · Lewisham East
I recognised
then, as I do now,
the deep turmoil that
family members experience
when they know that their
loved ones are dying,
or see them die.
The agonising distress
or pain that they
experience is something
that no one wants
for themselves or
their loved ones.
However,
I cannot shake from my
mind a conversation I had
with someone some time
ago about assisted dying.
They had been diagnosed
with HIV/AIDS before the
time of advanced medication
for this illness.
Their body was breaking down,
and they had been
informed that
their prognosis was bleak.
They said that
had assisted dying
been an option for them then,
they would have taken it.
However, it was not an option,
and they have since
been stabilised on
medication and are
in full-time work.
As a relative who
saw the inadequacy of
Ms Julie Minns MP
Labour · Carlisle
social care eat away
at the self-respect
of a once fiercely
independent woman,
leaving her to
conclude that she was a
burden and would
be better off dead,
I know that access
to every possible
form of support was
not there for her.
As the daughter who sat
at a hospital bedside,
having agreed to
the withdrawal
of invasive treatment,
only to watch my
semi-conscious mother scream
for water that was wrongly
withheld and writhe
in agony because specialist
palliative care was
only available nine to
five on Monday to Friday,
I know that access
to every form
of support was
not there for her.
Maybe there should be
a citizens assembly
Sir Bernard Jenkin MP
Conservative · Harwich and North Essex
on this question—it
is a subject that
would lend itself to
a citizens assembly.
[Interruption.] Well,
it would not take away
any power from this House.
This House would still
be able to decide,
but it would inform
the debate in a way
that the debate is
still not informed.
My mother and father passed
away in recent years,
and I am so grateful
that my mother
never had to confront
this question.
She often said, “Oh,
I just want to die.
I am just a burden on
the family.” Though she
would never have
qualified for this Bill,
I am so grateful
that there were never
any circumstances
that would possibly
have confronted her
with this question.
I say to colleagues who
supported the Bill before
Dame Karen Bradley MP
Conservative · Staffordshire Moorlands
and have wrestled sincerely
with the issue since:
you do not have to
repudiate the vote you
cast last time to vote
differently today.
You do not have to decide that
assisted dying can
never be right.
You do not have to
abandon the compassion
that led you to
support the principle.
You need only ask whether
this Bill, in this form,
on the evidence
before us today,
is safe enough for Parliament
to force it into law.
That is today's test.
There is no shame whatsoever
in concluding that
the answer to a different
question is different.
As a former mental health
doctor and someone who
Dr Ben Spencer MP
Conservative · Runnymede and Weybridge
has done research on
decision-making capacity,
I want to talk about stigma in
the brief time I have today.
I have looked after many
hundreds of people—perhaps
thousands—who have self-harmed
or attempted suicide.
Of course,
a desire for one's life
to end can be entirely
reasonable and an
understandable wish,
but it is often
a manifestation
of a treatable
mental disorder.
With the right intervention,
care and support,
people can get better.
They can look back and
say, "What was that about?
I'm so thankful I
didn't succeed" when
they get the care and
treatment they need.
The Bill refuses to
acknowledge that.
The report should
be more widely read,
Dr Kieran Mullan MP
Conservative · Bexhill and Battle
and I often wonder
why it did not
get the attention
that it deserved.
It found that between
1987 and 2001,
more than 450 NHS
patients had their lives
prematurely shortened
by healthcare staff.
They were mainly
elderly—the average age
being 81—but some
were as young as 61,
and more than 70% of
them had been admitted
to hospital not needing
palliative care or
being at the end
of their lives.